Guide to the John Canemaker Animation Collection MSS.040
Fales Library and Special Collections
John Canemaker Animation Collection
1903-2012
1970-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
Canemaker, John
MSS.040
81 Linear Feet (90 boxes)
John Canemaker (b. 1943) is an internationally recognized independent animator, animation historian, author, teacher and lecturer. Since 1988, he has directed the animation program at the Tisch School of the Arts' Kanbar Institute of Film and Television. He has also been a Guest Fellow at Yale University. Canemaker's interest in animation began in childhood, and it has moved him to write more than 100 articles on the subject, as well as several books, including the story of the making of Richard Williams' Raggedy Ann & Andy entitled: The Animated Raggedy Ann & Andy (1977). Canemaker's own films include:'The 40's' (1974), 'Bottom's Dream' (1983), 'The Hunger Project' (1987), animation sequences for 'The World According To Garp'(1981), 'You Don't Have To Die' (1988) which received an Academy Award, Confessions of a Stand-Up (1993), and Bridgehampton (1998). Canemaker began collecting the material that comprises this collection in the early 1970's, and eventually obtained a wealth of material about the history, technique,and cultural significance of animated films. Items include animation resources such as: documentary material, drawings, posters, storyboards, recorded interviews and lectures, personal research materials for his articles and books, and periodicals.
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into seven series.
Accretions are listed at the end of the container list and mirror the original organizational structure of the collection.
Missing Title
Series I: Documentary Material
Series II: Graphic Material
Series III: Book Collection
Series IV: Periodical Collection
Series V: Audio & Video Tape Collection
Oversize - Series I: Documentary Material
Oversize - Series II: Graphic Material
Accretions 2000 - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2000 - Oversize - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2001 - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2001 - Oversize - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2001 - Oversize - Series II: Graphic Material
Accretions 2003 - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2003 - Series II: Graphic Material
Accretions 2003 - Series VI: Major Projects
Accretions 2003 - Oversize - Series II: Graphic Material
Accretions 2008 - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2008 - Series II: Graphic Material
Accretions 2008 - Series III: Book Collection
Accretions 2008 - Series IV: Periodical Collection
Accretions 2008 - Series V: Audio & Video Tape Collection
Accretions 2008 - Series VI: Major Projects
Accretions 2008 - Series VII: Objects
Accretions 2008 - Oversize - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2012 - Series I: Documentary Material
Accretions 2012 - Series IV: Periodical Collection
Accretions 2012 - Series V: Audio & Video Tape Collection
Accretions 2012 - Series VI: Major Projects
Accretions 2012 - Oversize - Series I - Documentary Material
Accretions 2012 - Oversize - Series VI - Major Projects
Biographical Note
John Canemaker (b. 1943) is an internationally recognized independent animator, animation historian, author, teacher and lecturer. In 1980, he began teaching and developing the animation program at New York University, Tisch School of the Arts'; Kanbar Institute of Film and Television Department. Since 1988 he has directed the program and is currently a tenured full professor. From 2001-2002 he was Acting Chair of the NYU Undergraduate Film and Television Department.
Raised in Elmira, New York, Canemaker began an acting career which included off-Broadway and advertising work in New York City from 1961 to 1965. In 1967, after a two-year stint in the Army, Canemaker, with funds from acting assignments in TV commercials (he appeared in over 35 advertisements for major products), obtained his Bachelor of Arts degree from Marymount Manhattan College in 1974 and Master of Fine Arts in Film from New York University in 1976.
While studying for his Bachelor of Arts degree, Canemaker's childhood interest in animation revived. He began making sponsored animated shorts and wrote the first of more than 100 articles on animation history. His first book, the story of the making of Richard Williams' RAGGEDY ANN and ANDY, was published in 1977 as "The Animated Raggedy Ann and Andy." In 1982, he wrote the introduction to "Treasures of Disney Animation Art," and, in 1987, he published, "Winsor McCay - His Life and Art," and, in 1991, "Felix, the Twisted Tale of the World's Most Famous Cat." There followed "Tex Avery: The MGM Years" and "Before the Animation Begins: The Art and Lives of Disney Inspirational Sketch Artists (both in 1997), "Paper Dreams: The Art and Artists of Disney Storyboards" (1999), "Walt Disney's Nine Old Men and the Art of Animation" (2001), and "The Art and Flair of Mary Blair" (2003). Research material from all of these books now resides in the Fales Library. "Lucy Goes to the Country," a 1998 children's book collaboration with Joseph Kennedy, contains illustrations by Canemaker.
His research in the history of animation inspired two of his own films, REMEMBERING WINSOR McCAY (1976) and OTTO MESSMER and FELIX THE CAT (1977).
Canemaker's filmography includes independently-made animated shorts that are part of the permanent collection of New York's Museum of Modern Art. Among them: THE 40's (1974), STREET FREAKS (1975), CONFESSIONS OF ASTARDREAMER (1978), THE WIZARD'S SON (1981), BOTTOM'S DREAM (1983),CONFESSIONS OF A STAND-UP (1993), BRIDGEHAMPTON (1998), THE MOON AND THE SON: AN IMAGINED CONVERSATION (2004) a 28-minute film about Canemaker's father.
In the early 1980's, Canemaker animated several Children's Television Workshop films, TV commercials, and, in 1981, created the animation sequences for the Warner Bros. feature THE WORLD ACCORDING TO GARP. He designed and directed animation sequences in the Academy Award-winning HBO documentary YOU DON'T HAVE TO DIE (1988) and the Peabody Award-winning CBS documentary BREAK THE SILENCE: KIDS AGAINST CHILD ABUSE (1994).
JOHN CANEMAKER: MARCHING TO A DIFFERENT TOON, a DVD/home video collection of his films, is distributed by Milestone Film & Video/Image Entertainment. In addition, Canemaker writes regularly on animation for the New York Times and is on-camera and audio commentator for DVD versions of THE FANTASIA ANTHOLOGY, DUMBO, BEAUTY AND THE BEAST, PETER PAN, SNOW WHITE AND THE SEVEN DWARFS, CUT-UP: THE FILMS OF GRANT MUNRO, and WINSOR McCAY: THE MASTER EDITION. He has appeared on NBC's TODAY, PBS's NEWS HOUR WITH JIM LEHRER,and ENTERTAINMENT TONIGHT, and has lectured throughout the United States and in Brazil, Canada, England, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Slovakia, Spain, Switzerland, and Wales.
For more information, visit: http://www.johncanemaker.com
FILMOGRAPHY: Selected Personal Films:
Missing Title
THE MOON AND THE SON: AN IMAGINED CONVERSATION (2004)
BRIDGEHAMPTON (1998)
CONFESSIONS OF A STAND-UP (1993)
BOTTOM'S DREAM (1983)
THE WIZARD'S SON (1981)
CONFESSIONS OF A STARDREAMER (1978)
OTTO MESSMER AND FELIX THE CAT (1977)
REMEMBERING WINSOR McCAY (1976)
THE 40'S (1974)
STREET FREAKS (1974)
GREED (1974)
FILMOGRAPHY: Selected Sponsored Films:
Missing Title
RAID (1996) - R/Greenberg Assoc.
JET DRY (1996) - R/Greenberg Assoc.
LIVING FOSSILS (1995) - National Geographic Society.
BREAK THE SILENCE: KIDS AGAINST CHILD ABUSE (1994) - CBS special
ANGELS ON ICE (1994) - GMHC psa
SHELL OIL (1994)- R/Greenberg Assoc.
HOW TO GET BLESSED WITHOUT SNEEZING (1993) - Trinity Television
FREE RADICALS (1993) - Este Lauder/Pharmaceuticals
THE CREATIVE SPIRIT (1992) - PBS series
THE GALAXY CLASSROOM PROJECT (1992) - Hughes/Umbrella Ltd.
CIRCUS FOR LIFE (1992) - GMHC psa
SCIENCE EXPERIENCES (1992) - MacMillan McGraw-Hill/Terra
BEHIND THE SCENES (1992) - Learning Designs/PBS.
AIDS DANCE-A-THON (1991) - G.M.H.C. psa
DANCE IN AMERICA - EVERYBODY DANCE NOW! (1991) WNET/13
YOUNG PEOPLE AND RELATIONSHIPS (1991) Channing L. Bete Co.
BISON BINGE (1991) - CTW - 3-2-1 Contact
FLINTSTONES/JETSONS Interactive CD-ROM (1991) - R/Greenberg
HATE ON TRIAL (1991) - WNET/13
KIMBERLY CLARK/ NEW FREEDOM (1990) - Ogilvy & Mather
REQUEST PAY PER VIEW TV (1990) - E.W. Power Agency
WHAT'S UP, DR. RUTH? (1989) - Lifetime Television series
WARNING: DIETS MAY BE HAZARDOUS TO YOUR HEALTH (1989) - HBO special
FOOD `a la FLOYD (1989) - Lifetime Television series
K.C. JONES AND THE QUEST FOR NEVER-ENDING DIAPER DOMINATION (1989) - Huggies
Diapers - Ogilvy & Mather
YOU DON'T HAVE TO DIE (1988) - HBO special
LATE FOR DINNER (1988) - Prod.: Cinemax/New Star
THE HUNGER PROJECT (1988) - THP/The Leland Company
WALT DISNEY/SILVER SCREEN PARTNERS IV(1987) - Duncan & Katz
KOTEX (1987) - Kimberly Clark/Ogilvy & Mather
LYLE LYLE CROCODILE (1987) - Prod.: Michael Sporn Prod./HBO special
WHO'S THAT GIRL? (1987) - Broadcast Arts/Warner Bro. - title
JOHN LENNON SKETCHBOOK (1986) - producer: Yoko Ono
HOLIDAY INN (1986) TV commercial. - Bozell, Jacobs, Kenyon & Eckart
PEE WEE'S PLAYHOUSE (1986) - CBS/Broadcast Arts
THE ADVENTURE (1986) - Michael Sporn/CTW
LITTLE NEMO (1985) - Animated feature. Prod.: Tokyo Movie Shinsha
BRAINGAMES (1984) - HBO series
EFFECTIVE ORAL PRESENTATIONS (1984) - Tower, Perrins, Foster & Crosby
KAZ VS THE GYPSY MOTH (1983) - Chemical Abstracts Inc.
BENATAR (1983) - HBO/Rising Star Inc. - title
CAMPUS COMEDY (1983) - HBO/Rising Star Inc. - title
DNA CONCERTO (1983) - 3-2-1 Contact/CTW
WHAT DO CHILDREN THINK OF WHEN THEY THINK OF THE BOMB? (1983) - PBS special
THE WORLD ACCORDING TO GARP (1982) -Warner Bros.
LAUGHTER IS GOOD MEDICINE (1981) - Prod.: Billy Budd Films
CATCH A RISING STAR'S 10TH ANNIVERSARY (1981) - HBO title
80 MILLION YEARS AGO (1981) - 3-2-1-Contact/CTW
MUSIC MUSIC MUSIC (1981) - CBS Cable
WOMAN OF THE YEAR (1981) - Kander and Ebb stage musical/Michael Sporn Productions
CAPTAIN KANGAROO'S WAKE-UP (1981) - Bruce Cayard Productions
ROCKY HORROR SHOW (1980) - Robert Fishko Productions
Sesame Street (1980): LETTER "M"; WASH YOUR HANDS; NEEDLE AND THREAD
SNEEZE; HUMMINGBIRD, ME AND MY "M" - Prod.: Bruce Cayard
NETHERLANDS (1979) - Hot Hero Sandwich/NBC. Prod.:Jerry Lieberman
HAPPY BIRTHDAY (1979) - CTW/3-2-1 Contact Prod.: Jerry Lieberman
THE ART OF OSKAR FISHINGER (1977) - CBS Camera Three documentary. Writer and on-camera host: John Canemaker
OSTRICH; KITTY; FLEA (1976) - CTW: The Electric Company - Prod.: Bruce Cayard
THE BOYS FROM TERMITE TERRACE (1975) - CBS Camera Three documentary. Writer and on-camera host: John Canemaker
DANCING BEAR (7 spots) - CBS/Captain Kangaroo (1975) - Prod.: Bruce Cayard
ANGRY GOAT - Sesame Street (1975) Prod.: Derek Lamb
SCARY THING; JUNGLE ROOM - Sesame Street (1974)- Prod.: Bruce Cayard
FILM RETROSPECTIVES:
Missing Title
JOHN CANEMAKER: MARCHING TO A DIFFERENT TOON ANIMATED FILMS 1978-1998 - Museum of Modern Art, New York, Friday, 6 November 1998.
THE ANIMATED FILMS OF JOHN CANEMAKER - The American Film Institute, Los Angeles, 24 January, 1987.
FILMS OF JOHN CANEMAKER - Lucca 20, Twentieth Annual Animation/Comic Book Festival - Lucca, Italy, 26 October - 2 November 1986.
AN EVENING WITH JOHN CANEMAKER - "Cineprobe" - Museum of Modern Art, New York, November 5, 1984.
BOOKS WRITTEN BY JOHN CANEMAKER:
Missing Title
The Art and Flair of Mary Blair. New York: Disney Editions, 2003.
Walt Disney's Nine Old Men and the Art of Animation. New York: Disney Editions, 2001.
Paper Dreams: The Art and Artists of Disney Storyboards. New York: Hyperion, 1999.
Lucy Goes to the Country: Alyson Wonderland, 1998. (Text by Joseph Kennedy, illustrations by John Canemaker).
Before the Animation Begins: The Art and Lives of Disney Inspirational Sketch Artists. New York: Hyperion, 1996.
Tex Avery: The MGM Years. Atlanta: Turner Publishing 1996.
Felix - The Twisted Tale of the World's Most Famous Cat. New York: Pantheon 1991; Da Capo, 1996; Dreamland (French ed.), 1996.
Winsor McCay - His Life and Art New York: Abbeville Press, 1987.
Treasures of Disney Animation Art. New York: Abbeville Press, 1982.
The Animated Raggedy Ann & Andy. Indianapolis/New York: Bobbs-Merrill Co. Inc. 1977.
Provenance
The John Canemaker Animation Collection was donated to the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library, New York University, through aformal agreement signed by the Library and John Canemaker on August 18, 1988. Additional material was donated in 1991, 2000, 2001, 2003, 2008 and 2012.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Scope and Content Note
Canemaker began collecting this material in the early 1970's establishing a rich resource devoted to the history, technique, and cultural significance of film animation. The collection has been enlarged with subsequent donations from Canemaker of additional material of historical and contemporary interest. The collection serves the needs both of Canemaker's students at the University's Tisch School ofthe Arts and of all researchers in the history and technique of film animation.
The John Canemaker Animation Collection housed in the Fales Library consists of documentary and graphic materials and is asource of information on personalities and subjects, both American and foreign, important to the history of film animation.
While the collection includes copies of original material dating from the beginnings of film animation at the end of the nineteenth century, the original material concentrates on the late 1970's and the 1980's. Significant portions of the collection relate to Walt Disney and hisstudio, and to Canemaker's own extensive creative and research activity, and publications.
SERIES DESCRIPTIONS:
NOTE: The container list has some anomalies that warrant explanation. Items in the original collection have been listed in alphabetical order by subject in precedence over physical location of an item. In other words, box 21, folder 171 may be referred to a number of times because it contains information on a few different persons or films. Functionally, the container list was made into an index/container list in the interest of assisting researchers in finding pertinent material on a particular topic. Initially, new material and indexed material were then inserted into the alphabetical sequence of the series and subseries but maintained in a separate box. The end result is that one will come upon a folder that is not in the same box as the previous item listed in the folder sequence of the series. There are also numerous "see" references within each series' alphabetical sequence.
Beginning with new material received after 2000, Accretions were maintained (See Accretions for 2000, 2001, 2003 and 2008). Here, new material was processed according to the original series-subseries structure, but kept separate from the original collection - no interfiling was done.
SERIES I: Documentary material
Series I consists of documentary material placed either in Subseries A, when it deals with more than one personality or with a general topic in animation, or in Subseries B, when the material is primarily about or by one personality. This is an adaptation of the "auteur" theory in film criticism, which credits the director as the most important creative force behind a film. In film animation, the "auteur" is usually the working animator, but producers, directors, studio owners (e.g., Walt Disney and Walter Lantz) and character voices (e.g., Mel Blanc and June Foray) are also accorded individual attention in this subseries.
Documentary material includes:
1.Manuscript and published versions of interviews with leading personalities in film animation.
2. Texts of animation courses.
3. Canemaker's research notes on people and films.
4. Correspondence.
5. Film production/work drafts, budgets, scripts, proposals, action outlines, and other production information.
6. Copies or originals of newspaper and periodical articles.
7. Flyers, brochures, catalogs, public relations and press releases relating to films, screenings, animation companies and festivals.
8. Resumes and biographies.
The material in each folder is arranged chronologically in the following order: correspondence; other related material; newspaper and periodical articles.
Subseries A: Subjects.
The largest amount of material in this subseries consists of programs from animation film festivals and screenings (1967-1987), representing the work of hundreds of animators from around the world. The programs, often richly illustrated, are a useful source for compiling filmographies and for biographical data. Information about foreign film festivals in the International files provides an overview of a particular country's animated film production.
Many illustrated catalogs, issued between 1977 and 1988 by Gallery Lainzberg, Museum Graphics, Sotheby, and others, are included under "Art and Collecting" and provide information about animators and films. Primarily, however, this material is interesting for showing the development of animation art as a "collectible." Catalogs in Subseries A include works of more than one animator; catalogs devoted to one animator are filed under the name in Subseries B.
The Walter Lantz Conference on Animation, sponsored by the American Film Institute in 1987 and 1988, published a volume titled, each year, The Art of the Animated Image, with the subtitle "an Anthology" in 1987 and "Storytelling in Animation" in 1988. John Canemaker edited the 1988 edition. Besides containing transcripts of panel discussions, there are contributions by historians and practitioners of animation.
Material about animation in the United Kingdom, is the largest in the International category and contains items collected during Canemaker's 1979 trip to England.
The Theory and Technique folder contains the text of a 1936 layout training course by Tom Codrick and Charles Philippi; material on an animation seminar at the New School in 1979; and articles relating to technical aspects of animation and the new field of computer animation.
The UCLA Oral History of the Motion Picture in America interviews (1969) have been sorted among the interviewees' folders: Tex Avery, Dave Fleischer, Fritz Freleng, and Richard Huemer. The Huemer folder also contains correspondence Canemaker had with UCLA regarding restrictions on the use of Huemer's interview.
Art Babbitt, a Disney animator, gave a series of lectures in London in July, 1973. There are two copies of these lectures, one on acid-free paper, and five interviews (1971-1979) by Canemaker with this important artist.
John Canemaker's own career as an historian and practitioner of animation spans the years from 1973, when he first visited the Disney Studios, to the animation he created for the 1988 Academy Award winning documentary, YOU DON'T HAVE TO DIE. The general folders also include documentation on Canemaker's military, acting, and university careers (1965-1974). While his journalistic work generally is filed under the subjects and people treated, material from his books and films is included. Series I contains documentary material and Series II, the artwork for the films. In addition to the technical aspects of filmmaking, the materials collected give insight into the problems of financing and the teamwork required to produce a film. The complete screenplay of THE WORLD ACCORDING TO GARP is in this series. Reviews and articles about the films evaluate the results of the enormous effort involved. Donald Crafton's 321-page, 1977 Yale University dissertation on Emile Cohl, a French pioneer of animation, and articles dating from 1937 to 1973 are included.
The Walt Disney material relates to the productions of his studio regardless of animator. Additional Disney material will be found in folders devoted to animators whose careers include work at the studio (e.g., Babbitt, Johnston, Kinney, Klein, Thoams, Tytla). Items in the General folders include articles about Disney and his studio (1932-1985), a 1935 list of books in the Disney Studio Library, and some unsigned letters from Walt Disney to Ub Werks (1928).
Among the richest documentary items about individual films are the analyses of ALICE IN WONDERLAND; inter-office memos about DON QUIXOTE; production/work drafts for DUMBO, FANTASIA, and THE JUNGLE BOOK. Comments by author P.L. Travers on the film script for MARY POPPINS are included. Information on other Disney productions includes release sheets for 21 features, giving credits for films in the period 1940-1985, and a 47 page listing of shorts (titles, dates, plots) from the period 1928-1943.
Oskar Fischinger and his wife Elfriede, early refugees from Nazi Germany, are represented in the collection through letters and items sent to Canemaker by Elfriede Fischinger. Although later acclaimed for his paintings, Fischinger did early work in animation. Included in these folders are copies of letters between Leopold Stokowski and Fischinger about FANTASIA.
Subseries B: People.
A sampling of the artists is a veritable Who's Who of animation from FELIX THE CAT to ROGER RABBIT: Max and Dave Fleischer, Otto Messmer, Bill Tytla, Richard Williams are a few of the creative talents represented in correspondence, interviews, and other documents in Series I: B.
SERIES II: Graphic material
Series II, which consists of the extensive graphic material Canemaker has collected over the years, has been divided into three subseries according to form in order to facilitate archival storage: artwork, posters, and flip books. Within the subseries, when applicable, materials have been alphabetically arranged by name of animator or creator. Posters have been given a descriptive title and arranged alphabetically in the special collections map case. Other oversize graphic material is also stored in the map case.
Graphic material includes:
1. Storyboards, layouts, cels, frame-by-frame analyses and other artwork used in producing animated films.
2. Sketchbooks.
3. Non-animation drawings such as caricatures.
4. Illustrations used in books about animation.
Subseries A: Artwork.(in Oversize boxes)
Canemaker's collected artwork for the JOHN LENNON SKETCHBOOK, which was commissioned by Yoko Ono, includes copies of 25 drawings made by Lennon. Miscellaneous artwork by Canemaker contains self-portraits, sketchbooks of random work, and early sketches for his films. Storyboards for THE WIZARD'S SON and THE WORLD ACCORDING TO GARP are stored in the map case.
Artwork by other animators includes thirty 20"x40" photostats (map case) of Disney backgrounds, action drawings, story sketches, etc.; illustrations used in TOO FUNNY FOR WORDS, by Frank Thomas and Ollie Johnston; and 6 cels, approximately 70 blue pencil drawings, and eight story sketches for Richard Williams' RAGGEDY ANN and ANDY.
Subseries B: Posters.(in Oversize boxes)
This series includes posters for conferences and festivals which depict favorite cartoon characters.
Subseries C: Flip Books.
The 53 flip books in this series range from early French works to avant garde creations as well as instructions on making flip books.
SERIES III:Book Collection
The book collection is housed in the Fales Library. The books have been catalogued in Bobcat. A keyword or related name search with the name Canemaker will retrieve the records for the books.
SERIES IV: Periodical Collection.
These items are housed in the Fales Library. A list of the periodicals is available in the Reading Room.
SERIES V: Audio and Video Tape Collection.